Guide to the Records of the Philomathean Society RG 30
New York University Archives
Records of the Philomathean Society
1832-1888
RG 30
New York University Archives
1.0 linear feet
The Philomathean Society was one of two literary societies founded in 1832 at the University of the City of New York (NYU). The Philomatheans were notable for organizing skillful debates, speeches and essays, and they published a number of poems and speeches over the course of nearly 60 years. The Philomathean Society disbanded in 1891.
The Philomathean Society.
Related Material at the New York University Archives
Poem, " The Future," by W.A. Butler, 1825-1902, 10th Anniversary of the Philomathean Society, 27, Oct. 1842 (NYU BP 116a)
The Philomathean, v. 1-2, Jan. 1874 - May 1875 (NYU Q9)
Jordan, Philip D., William Salton, Philomathean. Photostatic negative of article from Annals of Iowa, 3d series, v. 18, pp. 295-312. Includes description of 19th century literary societies (NYU Rp)
Picture of Philomathean Hall (LD7 K8)
Picture of Philomathean Room (Slide Collection Box 1, #41)
Debate, 1881, in Brainerd 1 Scrapbook, pp. 39-40, 53, 75. Clipping Collection, Brainerd.
Arrangement
The Records of the Philomathean Society consist of three series: official correspondence, meetings, and memorabilia. Each series is arranged in chronological order.
Scope and Contents
This small and incomplete collection of Philomathean Society records consists of minutes (1832-36, 1851-64 only), membership lists, constitutions and by-laws, resolutions, invitations and programs for meetings, and memorabilia, dating mainly from 1832 through the late 1860s. Official records are included in bound volumes of manuscript documents. There is a resolution protesting the projected closing of the University's Academic Department in 1881. An invitation to honorary membership for Martin Van Buren, dated 1841, which President Van Buren accepted, is found in Box 2, folder 6. A letter of gift dated 1940 accompanies the badges (Box 2, folder 8) and gives biographical data about their owner, George R. Howe (ex 1868).
History of the Philomathean Society
The Philomathean Literary Society of the University of the City of New York (New York University) was founded in October 1832, the same month in which the first classes were held. The 12 students who founded the Society also adopted a series of resolutions that became the foundaton of its constitution in 1835. As one of two literary societies (the founding of the Eucleian Literary Society also occurred in this period) on campus, the Philomatheans were known for their "exercises in Debating, Oratory, and Composition."
Although documentary evidence about the Philomatheans is scarce, according to Chancellor Henry MacCracken and Professor Ernest G. Sihler in their historical volume Universities and their Sons: New York University (Volume 1, 1901 - available in the NYU Archives), the Philomatheans, like the Eucleians, were given a room in the University building during the 1830s. It was described as "fitted up in a style of taste and elegance highly creditable to the young gentlemen members." Indications of the importance of Philomathean rituals include the vote taken on June 7, 1833 that "members wear a badge on all occasions" (a badge and a pin are included in this collection, Box 2, folders 8 and 9).
The Philomatheans apparently published some of the poems and speeches delivered at Philomathean or joint Philomathean-Eucleian meetings (see attached list). Two slender volumes of The Philomathean, "A Monthly College Journal Published by the Philomathean Society," which are in the NYU Archives (for the years 1874-1875) are the only remaining evidence of magazine publishing. The Philomatheans remained in existence until 1891. University catalogues and yearbooks only refer to the Eucleians after that year.
In addition to this small collection and the MacCracken-Sihler history, the researcher should consult the attached list of Philomathean materials in the New York University Archives and New York University Archives' Finding Aid for the Records of the Eucleian Society.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Johnson, John Taylor; New York University.; Philomathean Society (New York University).; University of the City of New York. Eucleian Society.; University of the City of New York.; American literature |x Societies, etc.; Bound Volumes of Manuscripts Documents.; Constitutions and By-laws.; Correspondence.; Debates and debating.; Membership lists.; Memorabilia.; Minutes.; New York (State) |z New York.; Programs (documents).; Resolutions (administrative records).; Students |x Conduct of life.
- Series I: Official Correspondence
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I: Official Records ("v" indicates a volume and "f" indicates a folder)
  - Minutes, 1832-1836 (Box 1, Folder 1v)
  - Membership Books, 1832-1888 (Box 1, Folder 2v)
  - Membership Books, 1832-1861 (Box 1, Folder 3v)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, 1835, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Resolutions, including re closing of Academic Department, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Membership invitations, regular and honorary, 1841, [1865?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Meetings
  - Invitations, lists, programs (incomplete), 1837-1866 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series III: Memorabilia
  - Class badge and Philomathean badge belonging to George Rowland Howe, with accompanying letter of gift, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Pin belonging to John Taylor Johnston, 1839 (Box 2, Folder 9)